# Paul J. Mello

 $\blacksquare$  mello.pauljason@gmail.com |  $\blacksquare$  (650)-477-7074 |

in pauljasonmello

paulimello |

>\_ paulimello.dev

• Half Moon Bay, California

SUMMARY: As an Artificial Intelligence graduate student with a deep curiosity for the fundamental truths of nature, I've concentrated my research on the nexus of generative AI, deep learning, and information theory. Drawing from this expertise, I've crafted neural solutions with the aim of solving, optimizing, and re-framing real world problems.

## EDUCATION

## Artificial Intelligence — Master of Science

Aug 2021 - May 2024

Charles W. Davidson College of Engineering

San José State University, California

Related Coursework: Deep Learning, Autonomous Systems, Data Science

#### Computer Science — Bachelor of Science | Mathematics, Philosophy - Minor

Aug 2016 - May 2021

College of Engineering & Computer Science

Sacramento State University, California

Related Coursework: Machine Learning, Software Engineering

Honors: Dean's List Recipient

# Work Experience

#### Information Processing in Diffusion Processes — Master's Thesis

May 2022 - May 2024

- Currently researching the information processing capabilities of generative AI in denoising neural networks.
- Leveraged novel techniques to discover fundamental connections between previously independent processes.

## Flower Classification — Kaggle Competition

Jan 2022 - May 2022

- Co-developed a TPU based classification model achieving a 12/162 leaderboard ranking.
- Led a team strategy to utilize weighted ensembling across well-established models, and applied novel data augmentation techniques to achieve a highly accurate classification model.

#### Population Projection — Course Project

Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

• Utilized machine learning and time series forecasting on World Bank Data to predict global population trends, uncover hidden patterns through statistical analysis, and enhance understanding via data visualization.

#### Amputee Rehabilitation Software — Capstone Project

Aug 2020 - May 2021

- Directed an 8-person team in close partnership with medical specialists to craft algorithmic approaches to address the needs and challenges of amputees through individualized care.
- Engineered a visualization application allowing medical professionals to manage and interact with patient data across devices.

#### Competitive Director — Sacramento State Club

Aug 2018 - Dec 2019

- Held Big Sky's committee chair to facilitate intercollegiate competition between dozens of universities.
- Directed over a dozen concurrently competing teams across various sports, tournaments, and divisions.
- Increased club enrollment by 2,000% through implementing a scalable club framework.

## TECHNICAL PROJECTS

## Image Annotation Generator — Course Project

Aug 2022 - Dec 2022

• Developed and optimized an image captioning machine learning method which enhanced caption accuracy using term frequency balancing through manual and SMOTE methods.

#### Stock Market Chatbot — Personal Project

OCT 2021 - DEC 2021

• Created a machine learning chatbot to retrieve and relay real time NYSE data through Alpha Vantage API calls.

# SKILLS

## Programming Languages and Libraries

- Libraries: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, tinygrad
- Languages: Python, R, C, C++, SQL, Java

#### Frequently Used Tools

- SSH, HPC, S3, AWS
- Git, GitHub, GitLab